<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rationality on Isabel Dahlgren</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/rationality/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rationality on Isabel Dahlgren</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/rationality/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Normal situations, abnormal norms</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/normal-situations-abnormal-norms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/normal-situations-abnormal-norms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most people lead a comfortable 9-5 life. You go to work, work away, go home, sometimes seeing friends or engaging in extracurriculars. Even so, sometimes you find yourself in unusual social situations, situations where a first-timer wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know how to behave. Here are some normal situations with abnormal social norms.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Flights:&lt;/strong&gt; On a 12-hour flight, you find a cross section of the population bored, tired and without Internet. In this willpower-reduced state, snobs dress in sweatpants and workaholics watch thrashy feel-good movies. A surprising number of people try napping&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, while others strike up conversations with strangers.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dates:&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;rsquo;s common for people taking steps to get to know new people, for example by attending local meet-ups; however, friend-seekers rarely try getting to know others well. Dates are among the few situations where people deliberately try building deep connections. Think about it: the purpose of a date is for two people, usually strangers, to become romantic partners. Pretty remarkable, right? Even more remarkable is that it sometimes works.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alcohol:&lt;/strong&gt; Alcohol creates a form of social anarchy. Moderately tipsy people are amusing &amp;ndash; they&amp;rsquo;re a bit like children, candid and ignorant of social norms, though they enjoy discussing grown-up topics.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work interviews:&lt;/strong&gt; A work interview is nothing at all like an ordinary conversation, despite appearances; it&amp;rsquo;s like an improv play where the interviewee tries selling themself and the interviewer maintains a poker face. The interviewee presents themself as the ideal employee: competent, reliable and a good coffee machine conversationalist&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music festivals:&lt;/strong&gt; During music festivals, thousands of sweaty people packed like sardines scream in unison while jumping up and down. Though they&amp;rsquo;re strangers, they share a sense of camaraderie, sometimes even sharing food and belongings&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Cult?&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summer camps:&lt;/strong&gt; There are summer camps for kids as well as adults, though the latter are sometimes called &amp;lsquo;retreats&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;get-aways&amp;rsquo;. The goal of most summer camps is for a group of strangers to pursue a common interest together and make new friends. Being in a remote place helps create a space for intimacy: the camp participants tacitly agree that &amp;lsquo;what gets said here stays here&amp;rsquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Military service:&lt;/strong&gt; Life in the military is famously totalitarian: it&amp;rsquo;s all about obeying your superiors. And if you do mandatory military service, you&amp;rsquo;re normally at the bottom of the pecking order. In no other setting is there such a clear hierarchy, and in no other setting is outright bullying socially acceptable.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These are all time-bound activities disconnected from everyday life, usually physically or by means of clothing, with extraordinary social norms. This makes them good settings for people-watching. Why study &amp;lsquo;man in a state of nature&amp;rsquo; &amp;ndash; an impossibility anyway &amp;ndash; if you can study &amp;lsquo;man in a state of society&amp;rsquo;?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What effective altruism misses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/what-effective-altruism-misses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/what-effective-altruism-misses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Effective altruism (EA) centres around a dozen or so &amp;ldquo;cause areas&amp;rdquo;, areas in which you can have a big positive impact. Common cause areas include AI safety, global poverty, farm animal welfare, biorisk, nuclear security and EA field building. As of a couple of years, AI safety is very hot within EA, with some of the EA golden boys, like Will MacAskill and Holden Karnofsky, making AI going well their top priority.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High school for heroes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/high-school-for-heroes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/high-school-for-heroes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;High school isn&amp;rsquo;t so much about preparing teenagers for adult life. In Sweden, you have a subject about cooking and personal finance, but only until secondary school. I think this makes sense: you only need one course on practical adult skills. After you know the basics, it&amp;rsquo;s all about practising IRL.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;But being a competent grown-up involves many other skills. It&amp;rsquo;s not just about successfully running a household &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s also a matter of &amp;ldquo;running yourself&amp;rdquo;. There are plenty of &amp;ldquo;serious&amp;rdquo; subjects we could fit in a standard high school curriculum. Here&amp;rsquo;s a vibe-based list:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Policy-making is complicated</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/policy-making-is-complicated/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/policy-making-is-complicated/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Things are more complicated than they first seem, especially when it comes to policy-making. Should Germany build nuclear power plants to reduce their carbon emissions? Should there be global standards for content moderation on social media platforms? How should we best mitigate the risk of future global pandemics?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I recently had the pleasure of getting to know more people working in policy and forecasting, and I quickly realised that I hadn&amp;rsquo;t internalised the complexity of the problems they face&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Here, I&amp;rsquo;ll list some intuition pumps for the difficulty of policy-related questions. For concreteness, I&amp;rsquo;ll focus on the first of the three above topics, nuclear power in Germany.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nerd trying to adapt to an AI economy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/nerd-trying-to-adapt-to-an-ai-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/nerd-trying-to-adapt-to-an-ai-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;i&#34;&gt;I. &lt;a href=&#34;#i&#34; class=&#34;hash&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Part of the reason I decided to study maths was because it seemed like the most useful subject. If I knew ML systems would never get better than GPT-2 at maths, I&amp;rsquo;d probably be of the same opinion today. But today&amp;rsquo;s state-of-the-art ML systems are far better than GPT-2. LLMs have excelled at maths and programming because maths- and coding-related tasks admit quick feedback, allowing for efficient reinforcement learning. Jobs involving applying maths and programming jobs could theoretically be automated within a few decades. The glory days of the nerd might be over soon.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On my relation to effective altruism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-my-relation-to-effective-altruism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-my-relation-to-effective-altruism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent more time engaging with the effective altruist (EA) community this year. Not just reading EA books and blog posts, but participating in seminars, attending conferences and going on EA retreats. For context, I&amp;rsquo;d viewed myself &amp;ldquo;EA adjacent&amp;rdquo; ever since I came across &lt;em&gt;The Life You Can Save&lt;/em&gt; back in high school. However, during my master degree, the prospect of graduating soon - of becoming an adult - made me reflect more carefully on EA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the joy of customising</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-the-joy-of-customising/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-the-joy-of-customising/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Why do so many people use Safari, the jarring black VSCode colour theme and Overleaf? Because it&amp;rsquo;s the default option.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Switching to a non-default option requires conscious effort. First, you need to realise that your current setup is suboptimal: the probability of your current setup being the optimal one is infinitesimal. But if you knew about the benefits of making a few small changes, you&amp;rsquo;d already have made them. So you do need to believe that switching is worthwhile, which, indeed, is a leap of faith.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On decision fatigue</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-decision-fatigue/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-decision-fatigue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;i&#34;&gt;I. &lt;a href=&#34;#i&#34; class=&#34;hash&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Life involves plenty of hard decisions. Should I switch jobs? Should I marry him? Should I move abroad? Then there are the &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; decisions: which pyjama to wear or which brand of laundry detergent to buy. Although it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter which option you choose here, choosing is hard. In fact, if you think of buying laundry detergent as an optimisation problem, taking into account things like social impact, price and quality, I&amp;rsquo;d expect the optimisation problem to be NP-hard! Here&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/07/22/choices-are-bad/&#34;&gt;Zvi&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On good conversations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-good-conversations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-good-conversations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;i&#34;&gt;I. &lt;a href=&#34;#i&#34; class=&#34;hash&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some studies suggest we spend 80-90% of our waking hours talking with others. For a normal person, that&amp;rsquo;s at least 12 hours (!) per day. We spend most of our working hours talking to others, whether it be in meetings, lectures or exercise classes. When we&amp;rsquo;re not working, friends, roommates or partners might be around. The hours add up.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why do we spend this much time talking with others? Above all, interesting conversations are among the greatest pleasures in life. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like a good conversation over a good meal. But talking with others can also be very productive. For example, talking with people smarter than you is a phenomenal way of learning. It&amp;rsquo;s like you&amp;rsquo;re downloading part of someone else&amp;rsquo;s worldview into your own head. Of course, there are other ways of achieving the same thing. However, in my opinion, one-on-one discussions come the closest to a loss-free download.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Look for opinions</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/look-for-opinions/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/look-for-opinions/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Opinionated people can be really annoying. Wherever they go, they try convincing you of their ideas. If you have an opinionated uncle, the Christmas dinner might be ruined by a bitter argument. I&amp;rsquo;ve certainly had bad experiences with a dinner-table conversations turning into feuds. For this reason, I used to try having fewer opinions. I somehow assumed this meant being more open-minded and mature. Well, no.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;welcoming-opinions&#34;&gt;Welcoming opinions &lt;a href=&#34;#welcoming-opinions&#34; class=&#34;hash&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Actually, there are plenty of benefits of actively trying to form more opinions. Even about topics you don&amp;rsquo;t know particularly well. If you learn with a view towards arguing, then you&amp;rsquo;ll pay closer attention to the material. I think this has to do with anchoring. If you pick a stance, even at random, you&amp;rsquo;ll be more emotionally invested. Holden Karnofsky summarised it neatly in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cold-takes.com/learning-by-writing/&#34;&gt;Learning by Writing&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Useful thought experiments</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/useful-thought-experiments/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/useful-thought-experiments/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Philosophers love thought experiments. Thought experiments are hypothetical scenarios meant to tease out our intuitions about an argument or theory. For example, here&amp;rsquo;s a classic thought experiment, due to Robert Nozick:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Suppose there were an experience machine that would give you any experience you desired. Superduper neuropsychologists could stimulate your brain so that you would think and feel you were writing a great novel, or making a friend, or reading an interesting book. All the time you would be floating in a tank, with electrodes attached to your brain. Should you plug into this machine for life, preprogramming your life&amp;rsquo;s experiences?&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
