<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Essay on Isabel Dahlgren</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/essay/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Essay on Isabel Dahlgren</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/essay/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>On shame</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-shame/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-shame/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There are many negative emotions: envy, anger, fear, worry, sadness, to name a few. Positive emotions don&amp;rsquo;t carry as much nuance. When you&amp;rsquo;re asked how you&amp;rsquo;re doing, assuming you&amp;rsquo;re doing good, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably reply you&amp;rsquo;re simply &amp;lsquo;doing good&amp;rsquo;. Positive emotions like happiness, fulfilment or excitement appear to be more strongly correlated with one another &amp;ndash; for this reason, they&amp;rsquo;re often lumped together under the generic term &amp;lsquo;happiness&amp;rsquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Among negative experiences, worry is the most prevalent. In a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gallup.com/analytics/349280/state-of-worlds-emotional-health.aspx&#34;&gt;2024 Gallup study&lt;/a&gt; where adults were asked which feelings they&amp;rsquo;d experienced &amp;lsquo;a lot&amp;rsquo; the previous day, 39% and 37% reported feelings of worry and stress, respectively. Next followed physical pain (32%), sadness (26%) and anger (22%)&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Techno-optimism - techno-altruism?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/techno-optimism-techno-altruism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/techno-optimism-techno-altruism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;You might think the average worker in the tech industry is a diehard capitalist, since tech is full of rich entrepreneurs. Moreover, many big tech companies appear to be driven more by money-making than by providing consumer value: Facebook didn&amp;rsquo;t connect us with friends and family and OpenAI didn&amp;rsquo;t remain a safety-oriented non-profit.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However, most tech hubs are overwhelmingly liberal: 64% of voters in San Fransisco are registered as democrats; 8% as republican. Many programmers also dream to create widely accessible software, software for anyone, rich or poor, with stable Internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What effective altruism misses</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/what-effective-altruism-misses/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/what-effective-altruism-misses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Effective altruism (EA) centres around a dozen or so &amp;ldquo;cause areas&amp;rdquo;, areas in which you can have a big positive impact. Common cause areas include AI safety, global poverty, farm animal welfare, biorisk, nuclear security and EA field building. As of a couple of years, AI safety is very hot within EA, with some of the EA golden boys, like Will MacAskill and Holden Karnofsky, making AI going well their top priority.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sanremese</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/the-sanremese/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/the-sanremese/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In Europe, you don&amp;rsquo;t have to travel far to experience a completely different culture. If you randomly select a point in Europe outside of Russia, you&amp;rsquo;re never further than &lt;a href=&#34;https://maps.app.goo.gl/oY6zXbdFeQCc6Xqo7&#34;&gt;10h by train from the nearest nation border&lt;/a&gt;. There are 44 countries and 24 official languages in Europe &amp;ndash; yet, the area of Europe is just 60% of the area of the American South.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I expected Sanremo to be like some of the towns by the French Riviera I&amp;rsquo;d visited when living in Aix, only with better ravioli and friendlier people. Although I wasn&amp;rsquo;t entirely wrong, I was far from correct.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On cities</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-cities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The 17th century was a century of rapid human progress. There was the Scientific Revolution. Philosophers like John Locke and Thomas Hobbes laid the groundwork for modern political thought, while René Descartes and Blaise Pascal made important contributions to philosophy more broadly. Meanwhile, in the arts, William Shakespeare redefined English literature, while Rembrandt changed the way artists approach their subjects.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The above mentioned people have something important in common, other than being extremely intelligent white men. They spent non-negligible parts of their lives in cities. In the 1600s, only &lt;a href=&#34;https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/long-term-urban-population-region?time=1500..latest&amp;amp;country=Eastern+Africa~Western+Europe~Korea~Central+Europe~OWID_EUR&#34;&gt;8%&lt;/a&gt; of the European population lived in cities. Many people spent their entire lives without setting foot in a big city. But there is a sense in which you need to spend some time in a city to become an influential historical figure, or at least if you wish to understand human societies. Cities tell thousands of tales about history, culture and economics.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On good hobbies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-good-hobbies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-good-hobbies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Everyone has hobbies, whether they recognise it or not. For example, workaholics who don&amp;rsquo;t seem to have any &amp;ldquo;normal&amp;rdquo; hobbies might be really into, say, writing slick SQL queries. Code golf is a hobby too. By definition, a hobby is something you do for pleasure when you&amp;rsquo;re not working. And for the record, writing slick SQL queries isn&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some hobbies are better than others, though. Examples of not-as-good hobbies include motorcycling (dangerous), graffiti painting (illegal) and doom-scrolling social media (depressing). A benchmark for hobby quality: ask whether your mom would like it. So, which hobbies would your mom like?&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sweden</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/sweden/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/sweden/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Everyone who has ever lived abroad gets homesick every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Swedes, I give you a postcard from a Stockholm-centric, homesick expat. Non-Swedes, here&amp;rsquo;s a highly biased tourist guide.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The best thing about Sweden? My favourite Swedes, for sure. I miss family and friends a lot.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Other than that, hearing Swedish jazz live. Hearing &lt;em&gt;Sakta vi gå genom stan&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Flykten från vardagen&lt;/em&gt; live. Or if Glenn Miller or Fasching is too pricey, you could just drop by KMH and enjoy up-and-coming jazz, all for free.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the perks of adulthood</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-the-perks-of-adulthood/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-the-perks-of-adulthood/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;i&#34;&gt;I. &lt;a href=&#34;#i&#34; class=&#34;hash&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I know you dread becoming an adult. Most adults seem to have such boring lives. Not that you&amp;rsquo;re having fun all the time either. High school biology isn&amp;rsquo;t that exciting. But at least your life outside of school is filled with novelty. That&amp;rsquo;s something. There&amp;rsquo;s something special about all those first times.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re just seeking novelty, you&amp;rsquo;ll be disappointed. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s the real reason you dread adulthood. While I don&amp;rsquo;t feel like an adult just yet, many of my friends have become Real Adults, being in stable relationships, getting high-paid jobs and moving abroad. So I&amp;rsquo;m beginning to understand the adult world. It&amp;rsquo;s not as bad as it seems, only very different.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On my relation to effective altruism</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-my-relation-to-effective-altruism/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 29 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-my-relation-to-effective-altruism/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent more time engaging with the effective altruist (EA) community this year. Not just reading EA books and blog posts, but participating in seminars, attending conferences and going on EA retreats. For context, I&amp;rsquo;d viewed myself &amp;ldquo;EA adjacent&amp;rdquo; ever since I came across &lt;em&gt;The Life You Can Save&lt;/em&gt; back in high school. However, during my master degree, the prospect of graduating soon - of becoming an adult - made me reflect more carefully on EA.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On question taste</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-question-taste/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-question-taste/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;i&#34;&gt;I. &lt;a href=&#34;#i&#34; class=&#34;hash&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Children like asking questions. Some of their questions are very hard: &amp;ldquo;Why do people die?&amp;rdquo;. Others questions expose our biases: &amp;ldquo;Couldn&amp;rsquo;t we invite the homeless man to dinner?&amp;rdquo; Then there are all the annoying questions: &amp;ldquo;When will we arrive?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In my experience, school didn&amp;rsquo;t teach us to ask questions - we were just taught how to answer them. To pass the test, you only had to memorise the material in the textbook.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On decision fatigue</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-decision-fatigue/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-decision-fatigue/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;i&#34;&gt;I. &lt;a href=&#34;#i&#34; class=&#34;hash&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Life involves plenty of hard decisions. Should I switch jobs? Should I marry him? Should I move abroad? Then there are the &amp;ldquo;easy&amp;rdquo; decisions: which pyjama to wear or which brand of laundry detergent to buy. Although it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter which option you choose here, choosing is hard. In fact, if you think of buying laundry detergent as an optimisation problem, taking into account things like social impact, price and quality, I&amp;rsquo;d expect the optimisation problem to be NP-hard! Here&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://thezvi.wordpress.com/2017/07/22/choices-are-bad/&#34;&gt;Zvi&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On good conversations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/on-good-conversations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/on-good-conversations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;i&#34;&gt;I. &lt;a href=&#34;#i&#34; class=&#34;hash&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Some studies suggest we spend 80-90% of our waking hours talking with others. For a normal person, that&amp;rsquo;s at least 12 hours (!) per day. We spend most of our working hours talking to others, whether it be in meetings, lectures or exercise classes. When we&amp;rsquo;re not working, friends, roommates or partners might be around. The hours add up.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Why do we spend this much time talking with others? Above all, interesting conversations are among the greatest pleasures in life. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing like a good conversation over a good meal. But talking with others can also be very productive. For example, talking with people smarter than you is a phenomenal way of learning. It&amp;rsquo;s like you&amp;rsquo;re downloading part of someone else&amp;rsquo;s worldview into your own head. Of course, there are other ways of achieving the same thing. However, in my opinion, one-on-one discussions come the closest to a loss-free download.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building time machines</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/building-time-machines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/building-time-machines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a folder on my computer called &amp;ldquo;Time machine&amp;rdquo;, where I collect files on today&amp;rsquo;s me. It&amp;rsquo;s not exactly an FBI record on myself, but rather like a digital self portrait. After doing this over a longer period of time, I&amp;rsquo;ll share the folder with future versions of people I care about.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;i&#34;&gt;I. &lt;a href=&#34;#i&#34; class=&#34;hash&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I like poring over old photos. I think it&amp;rsquo;s something I&amp;rsquo;ve picked up from my mom. She&amp;rsquo;s something of a camera terrorist &amp;ndash; she&amp;rsquo;ll always pull up the camera and have everyone else pose. As a teenager, I used to find this pretty embarrassing. But now I&amp;rsquo;m glad she ignored my complaints.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
